hi this is Eric Weinstein and welcome
back to my youtube channel so there are
two exogenously thinking a little bit
differently today the first is that this
is my office and has been my office for
about five years here at teal Capitol
and with reorganization I'm going to be
moving out of this office and the reason
that that's important is that some of
you have questioned why there is a
ghostly image on the glass window behind
me and I thought it would might be
interesting to talk about that and the
other thing that's motivating me is that
while I was sitting in a parked car I
was rear-ended rather suddenly and
dramatically yesterday the airbags and
the other car went off and I got to
thinking about with all of the things
that we do to try to extend life and
make life worth living we forget how
fragile it is and had things been a
little bit different I might have
sustained some some more serious
injuries and I was just put in mind of
what really is important to accomplish
before we leave this beautiful world and
those two things have me thinking about
a topic that I hadn't expected to
discuss which is the subject of who that
person is and the importance of having
an arch-nemesis so in my case I feel
very fortunate that I have selected an
arch-nemesis who really suits me and
since I don't have a fleet of Tesla's
and I don't have ski chalets all over
the world the one luxury item that I
have that many people don't is an
arch-nemesis and I thought I'd talk a
little bit about how important in our
genomicist can be and how you might
acquire one what thinking should go into
your process and what you might hope to
get out of it so in my case what my
belief is that an arch-nemesis is a
really important decision in your life
much like choosing a life partner or
what city you will live in
or what area you will choose in which to
build your skills so that you might have
a fulfilling profession I think when you
when you've taken arch-nemesis it's
important to realize that it's not
really about the cartoon relationships
that superheroes have with their their
principal enemies and arch-nemesis is
something much richer to me it is in
general a human being with whom you
share a tremendous amount but you differ
on some subset of issues where that
difference means that you cannot both
win and in my case what I'm very
sympathetic with is the objective of my
arch-nemesis and when I'm very what I'm
what I find myself
divided on from my arch-nemesis is the
method by which we are both trying to
get to this common destination so you
could think of this for example in terms
of the civil rights movement where
Martin Luther King and Malcolm X both
probably shared many goals which was
true liberation and equality for black
America but they probably differed a
tremendous amount on the means by which
they were willing to get there and both
of them held the other in a great deal
of respect but may have felt very very
sharply different from the other about
the modalities by which they were
interested in getting to that common
objective so in my case the objective
was to try to understand what the
physical world was all about what is
this place in which we are having this
conversation
what is the construct in which you're
viewing a YouTube video you can think
about this from the perspective of the
atoms in your screen or the photons of
light that are reaching your eyeballs
but
what is this strange place that that we
call reality and the gentleman who is
depicted over my shoulder on the on the
glass in dry erase ink is Garrett Lisi
and he was famous or infamous several
years ago as the surfer dude with a
theory of everything and he lives in
Maui has somehow never seemingly really
held a job that would lead to a career
he has made a couple of investment
decisions which have really worked out
to make sure that he doesn't have to
have to work so he has a very enviable
lifestyle but he's also willing to live
in a van with zero security so he's a
real risk taker and what's more he's
very interested in an approach to
finding a theory of everything or a
theory of reality if you will that I
think is quite interesting and beautiful
I just don't think that's going to work
based on a set of symmetries which are
called a Lee group 4 it's a fancy
mathematician way of saying a collection
of continuous symmetries but in his face
the Lee group he chose which was also
the lead group that I found most
interesting called e8 and it's a two
hundred and forty eight dimensional
beast of an object we can't really
visualize it and it is suggestive
because of ways in which it combines
what you might call regular vector
vector like objects with exotic spinner
like objects something but vectors is
what gives you photons and spinners is
what gives you electrons and so somehow
vectors and spinners are bound together
in this crazy object he ate and Garrett
decided to make that the centerpiece of
his attempt to unify physics now despite
the fact that I think here it's wrong
and I don't think what he's doing will
will work he is one of the only people
in the entire world who are willing to
put forward what might be termed
something like a theory of everything
now you can say that it's incomplete you
can say that it's inconsistent but it is
clearly an attempt to explain the world
that we live in using a very complicated
piece of mathematical machinery and
despite the fact that I don't believe
that it works or even can be made to
work it is still a direct attempt at
resolving the major puzzles of art of
our time rather than working on the
mathematical structure of physics so
it's an attempt at an actual physical
idea rather than an attempt at improving
the mathematics around physics hoping
that that will produce the answer so
here the here are the criteria that I
think are most important when choosing
an arch-nemesis first of all it should
be somebody that you you want to see in
this world you should be sad if some if
somehow your arch-nemesis were to meet a
bad end because you want that person to
be with you and competing with you for
the long haul
so it should be somebody that you would
be very upset if you found out that they
were suddenly dead and removed from this
mortal coil it should also be somebody
who accepts you as his or her
arch-nemesis I don't think you should
just go about deciding the Elon Musk or
or Donald Trump is your arch nemesis if
they've never even heard of you
much less they don't obsess about you so
I think it's important that there be a
level of yuechu ality and that you
choose your arch nemesis and the her
arch nemesis chooses you or said it
slightly differently that you both
recognize that this is the nature of
your relationship it should also be the
case that if you were to lose you might
want them to win that's that's a hard
thing to couple to the fact that in
order for them to win you would have to
lose but both of these conditions need
to be
met in general if my particular take on
physics which I called geometric unity
turned out to be vacuous I would want to
find out that Garrett actually had a
theory that was workable it would it
would give me no pleasure to find out
that he too was also incorrect so I
think that's a very complicated dynamic
to get going it would be better if the
person was roughly your age we shared
some of your characteristics I think you
need to be able to see some of yourself
in your arch-nemesis in my case I feel
like Garrett has been a renegade he has
broken rules but he's also been an
insider and an outsider he has a PhD in
physics which is better than I can say
where my PhD is in mathematics he has
been more outside the system I stayed
longer probably in the academic game
than he did so it's there is a sort of a
degree of comparability and the picture
that lies over my shoulder I started to
feel better about it when I saw into
Floyd Mayweather's home after he
defeated Conor McGregor and there was a
photograph taken of Floyd Mayweather
with giant pictures of him and Conor
McGregor inside of his home and so the
idea that you would actually want to
represent your arch-nemesis inside of
your personal space is actually it makes
complete sense to me so what I'd like
you to think about is whether or not
you're ready to choose an arch-nemesis
to let that be a motivational decision
to propel you to try to keep working on
something when you feel discouraged to
use an aspect of competition which is
healthy i i'm very often reminded of my
my good friend Peter Till's admonition
that competition is for
the idea that when you spend your time
focusing on someone else rather than
focusing on a very difficult problem you
often get distracted from what's really
important and you find yourself in this
kind of memetic rivalry
I think the choosing an arch-nemesis is
a is a slight exception to this
generally pretty good rule when I get
discouraged I don't feel like looking at
physics it does help me to think about
the fact that somewhere out there and
Gareth is catching a wave in the waters
off of Maui thinking about physics and
trying to push his theory forward so I
find that not dispiriting or enervating
but I actually find it energizing and
you know I realized that because I'm
gonna have to leave this office it falls
to me rather than some anonymous
cleaning person to remove this picture
off of off of the glass and it's on both
sides of the glass crystal veronik who
drew this in dry erase ink who is at
that point here its girlfriend drew it
on both sides of the glass and I
remember thinking that it it would have
to be me who would take it down because
I wouldn't want to allow anyone else to
remove that from from my life so if you
don't mind as a symbolic action I'm
going to involve you all in the removal
of this piece of artwork from from my
office in my life as I change offices
and I do want to say particularly to
young men consider that an arch-nemesis
isn't something that you have to wait
for when you find somebody with whom
you're competitive where you have a lot
of respect for that person and you want
that person to motivate you over a
lifetime and you feel ready to make this
decision remember you should only choose
one and it should be a long-term
relationship you should be in dialogue
with that arch-nemesis over time and it
should be energizing to you both
just want to say first of all thank you
very much please subscribe to my youtube
channel
without further ado I suppose the time
has come be well
[Music]
thanks for watching